Blue for constancy.
蓝色代表忠贞不渝
Flesh for flesh. Straw for plenty.
肉色代表鱼水之欢 麦秆代表丰衣足食
Red for justice.
红色代表公正不倚
Le Roi.
国王驾到
The Palace of Whitehall London 1638
伦敦怀特霍尔宫 1638年
Your cousin Harry is the envy of my court.
你表哥哈里赢尽我宫廷内的艳羡眼光
Let's ask God to bless this union.
让我们祈求上帝赐福予你们的结合吧
'On the night of my birth,
在我出生的那个夜晚
'a comet appeared in the sky and bells rang out.'
一颗彗星划过夜空 钟声彻夜长鸣
A girl.
是女孩
'The bells did not herald my birth...
钟声并非为了通报我的降临而响
'..but the killing of my mother's Catholic priest.
而是为了处决我母亲的天主教牧师
'For Catholicism in England was seen as high treason.
此时的英国 信奉天主教被定为叛国罪
'Cousin Harry was my father's heir,
哈里表哥是我父亲的继承人
'and my childhood playmate.'
也是我儿时的玩伴
This is where my mother's priest used to come and go.
这是我母亲以前的神父进出的通道
Follow me, Harry.
跟我来 哈里
Be brave.
勇敢点
Mother?
母亲
Harry and I have a play to show you.
我和哈里要演戏给你看
Two birds that grow up and marry.
两只小鸟长大后结成连理
Mother?
母亲
I am your servant.
我是你的仆从
Instruct me.
请指引我
Mother?
母亲
'The Virgin Mary told my mother to leave me behind
圣母玛莉亚指引我母亲要把我丢下
'and go to a nunnery in France.'
去法国一家修道院做修女
Angelica...
安吉丽卡
It is Our Lady's will that I give my life over to God.
将我的生命奉献给上帝是圣母的旨意
My bible is my farewell gift to you.
这本圣经是我送你的分别礼物
Please don't leave me!
请不要丢下我
'This was the day I lost my mother
就在这一天 我失去了母亲
'and put my soul into the balance.'
打破了我灵魂中善恶的天平
If there be a God that steals mothers, strike me down!
如果世上真有偷走我母亲的上帝 来劈死我啊!
There is no God! There is no God!
这世上没有上帝!没有上帝!
乱世妖姬 第一季第1集
-==http://www.ragbear.com==-
Why do you weep, Angelica?
你为何哭泣 安吉丽卡
Only for joy that this day has finally come.
只是为了这个日子喜极而泣
Make her ready.
替她打扮好
Harry, I've heard the Queen say
哈里 我听皇后说
Angelica was wild as a colt when first she came to Court.
安吉丽卡刚来到宫廷时就像小马般狂野
Her mother went to a nunnery in France, Highness,
陛下 她母亲丢下她法国做修女
and then her father died.
然后她父亲过世了
For a year or two, she was not herself.
有那么一两年时间里 她迷失了自我
They tell me she saw devils.
他们跟我说她见过恶魔
She was but a child, my Lord!
她当时只是个孩子 殿下
It was her mind was wild, not her.
狂野的是她的思想 而不是她的人
A wild bedfellow then.
那就是一个狂野的床伴了
I do love to see a woman with spirit, and a man to break it.
我倒挺乐见一个有激情的女人被一个男人征服
She needs not be broken, my Lord.
她不需要征服 陛下
In faith I hope she be broken, Harry,in this very night.
我倒确实想看她在今晚能被征服 哈里
She's played false else.
她从前那些都是装的
Your work awaits you.
有任务等着你去完成呢
Not work...
那不是任务
but the purest delight to me, my Lord.
对我来说是纯粹的愉悦 殿下
Angelica Fanshawe is a delight to all men, Harry.
安吉丽卡·范肖取悦所有的男人
It's nothing, Angelica.
没什么事 安吉丽卡
If it is nothing then why may I not see?
既然没事为什么不让我看
Shall Honest John Lilburne...
是否诚实的约翰·李尔本
not speak the truth
不应该把国王所谓的
about this King that tells us God gave him his throne?!
君权神授的真相告知世人
I say to you, he is a tyrant
我跟你们说 他是一个暴君
that will not let his Parliament sit!
他阻止议会议事
Charles Stewart has no divine right.
查尔斯·斯图亚特的君权并非神授
For writing this I am whipped!
因为写了这句话 我要承受鞭刑
Will you recant, John?
你愿意撤回声明吗 约翰
The King promises your freedom
只要你否定你的传单
if you'll renounce your pamphlet.
国王就答应恢复你的自由
My liberty is his to take...
他只能剥夺我的自由
..but not to give.
但无权赐予
I am free-born John Lilburne!
我约翰·李尔本的自由是与生俱来的
Beg him to recant, madam!
请求他撤回声明吧 夫人
Do not recant, John.
不要撤回 约翰
Plague Pits at the Spitel Field Near London
瘟疫在伦敦附近的斯彼特菲尔德盛行
'I closed my eyes and lived in the dark,
我闭上双眼让自己在黑暗中生存
choosing not to see the world outside was sick and running mad.
我选择对外面病态而疯狂的世界视而不见
Read his pamphlet.
读读他的传单
Read and remember. For Justice and Liberty.
阅读并铭记 为了正义和自由
Your husband, madam?
是你丈夫吗 夫人
Aye. Honest John Lilburne.
是的 诚实的约翰·李尔本
Whipped for raising his voice for justice and liberty.
因为伸张正义和自由而受到鞭刑
Welcome to Babylon, sir.
欢迎来到巴比伦 先生
Justice and liberty?
正义和自由?
He is mistook, madam.
他搞错了 夫人
There's nought but these...
这个世界上除了这个没有别的
since time began.
自古如此
Well, Sexby...
哇 塞斯比
I thought you were long dead by now.
我还以为你早都已经死了呢
I am at your service, Highness.
随时听候你的差遣 陛下
No-one left to kill in Germany?
德国人都杀完了吗
Not a one left to piss against a wall, Highness.
男人都被杀得一个不留了 殿下
Well, you've travelled in vain. I have no need of you.
不过你白来了 我不需要你
Yet I heard talk of a fight to come here in England.
可我听到英国开始有了一些抗争
That the King must let his Parliament sit
请愿说 国王若想征收更多的税
That their heads buzz with grievances against him.
听说他们的头脑里满是对他的不满
That this will not be settled by talk.
听说这一切并不能用谈判平息
Dear God, who is she?
上帝呀 她是谁
Remember the sewer you were born in
记住你出生的那臭水沟
and the hag that gave you life!
以及生下你的那个女巫
Come to me later.
过些时候来找我
There is a service you may perform for me.
有一件事要你替我去办
But there'll be no fight in England, Sexby.
只是英国将不会有抗争的 塞斯比
May I speak with you, my Lady?
我能跟你说句话吗 夫人
Let her speak.
让她说吧
Quickly, madam, for I am waited on at the altar.
快说吧 夫人 他们在圣坛等我呢
My Lady, I am the wife of a man much misunderstood,
夫人 我是那个被严重误解的
Honest John Lilburne,
诚实的约翰·李尔本的妻子
that was whipped just now...        Whipped?
他正在受到鞭刑        鞭刑?
Aye, most cruelly,
是的 极尽残忍的
and will die in the Fleet unless a voice like yours
他将会死在舰队河监狱的
be raised up to help him.
除非能有你这样的人替他说句话
Wait!
等等
You might ask a favour of her Majesty on your wedding day.
你在婚礼那天也许可以请求皇后帮帮忙
My Lady, Lilburne is the villain that
夫人 李尔本是一个写谎言
writes lies about His Majesty.
诽谤国王的坏人
Madam, tell your husband
夫人 跟你丈夫说
there's no greater soul on this earth than the King.
这个世界上没有比国王更高尚的人了
He is my second father.
他是我的再世父亲
Then Honest John must die...
那诚实的约翰就必须要死了
and there is no liberty in this land.
这个国家根本没有自由
The garter! Yes!
吊袜带 吊袜带
No, no, no, no!
不要 不要 不要
Over here! Me, Angelica! Me!
这边 给我 安吉丽卡 给我
I will have them both, sir.
两个我都要
Let me be your friend a while longer.
让我多做一会儿你的朋友
My boy Harry.
我的男孩哈里
You'll always be my best friend.
你永远都将是我最好的朋友
But now I must be a husband.
但现在我必须要做你丈夫
And you will be the best husband a woman ever had.
而你将是一个女人所梦寐以求的最好丈夫
What, Harry? Not at your work yet?
怎么了 哈里 还没开始行事呢
A drink of sack.
喝杯酒
To make a "boy" lusty.
让小男孩变得勇猛一些
Well, then, "my boy Harry..."
好吧 "我的男孩哈里"
To it.
开始吧
He is the King's nephew.
他是国王的侄子
And a brave fighter.
是个勇敢的斗士
You must be brave too now, Harry.
你现在也要勇敢起来 哈里
You must not call me "boy".
你不能再叫我"男孩"了
I will be a boy no longer.
我再也不是男孩了
Husband, then.
那就叫夫君
Fanshawe House near Oxford
范肖宅 牛津附近
Do your worst.
使出你的杀招吧
'So Fanshawe married Fanshawe.
就这样范肖家跟范肖家联姻了
'Harry did not wed the house and land -
哈里娶的不是房屋和土地
'they were his already.
因为本来就属于他
'I did not wed the name -
我嫁的也不是姓氏
'that was mine already.
因为它原本就是我的姓
'We married for love.'
我们因爱而结合
My serve, sir. Thank you.
该我发球了 谢谢
Mistress Lilburne.
李尔本夫人
My Lady looks well.
夫人近来无恙
Lilburne?
李尔本
You have met before?
你们以前见过?
Your wife was kind enough to spare a word
贵夫人在婚礼当天曾仁慈地
on the day of your wedding, sir.
与我说过几句话
My husband knows not that I am here. He would not beg.
我丈夫不知道我来这里 他不愿乞求
Indeed. For I have read his letter.
确实如此 我拜读了他的来信
As well as his pamphlet, The Work Of The Beast,
还有他的文章
which he was loving enough
他还真够仁慈地
to send me as someone connected to His Majesty.
把这些东西寄给我这个与国王关系紧密之人
And indeed he does not beg -
他还确实没有乞求
he demands that I intercede on the side of "justice" and "liberty"
他要求我为"正义"和"自由"去游说
Perhaps you have not read his pages.
或许你没读过他的传单吧
Sir, some of the pages are mine.
先生 有一部分是我写的
John and I are of one mind and one flesh.
我和约翰同心共志
Please, sit. You are weary.
请坐吧 你很疲惫的样子
Indeed, Madam.
确实如此 夫人
For I have walked from London
我从伦敦徒步前来
to speak to you only the truth, I swear.
只是为了跟你诉说真相 我发誓
You have walked to no purpose, madam. She plays with "truth"
可惜你徒劳无益 夫人 她玩弄"真相"
as her husband plays with "liberty" and "justice".
而她丈夫玩弄"自由"和"正义"
I came not to play at anything, sir,
我来不是为了扮演什么 先生
but to save my husband from a slow death in the Fleet Prison.
只是为了拯救我被关在舰队河监狱等死的夫君
For I know not how he will live
除非有人替他求情
except a voice is raised up for him,
否则我真不知道他该如何才能活下来
for I think the truest man in England.
他是我认为全英国最诚实的男人
And though he will not beg, I will.
尽管他不愿乞求 我愿意
His demand is only that the King let the Parliament sit
他仅仅是要求国王让议会重新召开
so he may hear the grievances of his people.
如此他就能听到臣民们的疾苦
Husband? May we not hear...?        We?
夫君? 我们能不能不要让...      我们?
I fare you well, madam.
失陪了 夫人
You may go.
你走吧
You must never again interfere in matters you cannot understand.
从今往后不许再插手一些你并不了解的事
Give me that!
把它给我
Did you burn yourself?
烫到你的手了吗
Why do you stare at me always?
你为什么一直盯着我
Wait.
等等
When you were sent here,
当你被派到这里的时候
Prince Rupert said you were a good man for a fight.
鲁珀特王子说你很擅长打斗
I want you to take me to the Fleet Prison.
我想要你带我去舰队河监狱
How will the gaoler make his living
监狱看守不运进酒和妓女
unless he bring in wine and whores?
怎么能养家糊口?
I had thought there would be dungeons.
我还以为会有地牢呢
There are, my lady. And there with Lilburne they'll sit,
有的 夫人 李尔本他们就在那里
except the mob that reads his pamphlets came to burn the gaol down.
除了那些读了他的传单跑去烧监狱的暴徒
I must see your face, madam.
我必须要看到你的脸 夫人
I cannot.
不行
We must have your face, madam, or your name.
我们必须要看到脸 或者你的名字 夫人
I come to be of service to you, Master Lilburne.
我是来为你效劳的 李尔本先生
How, madam?
效劳什么 夫人
If you would but listen, my Lady will tell you.
如果你能好好倾听 夫人会告诉你的
I wish to help you to His Majesty's forgiveness.
我想帮你向国王请求宽恕
He's a just, wise, and merciful man.
他是一个公正英明而且仁慈的人
Forgiveness?!
宽恕?
For I think you are a sincere and godly man.
我觉得你是一个真诚善良的人
But you do not know His Majesty's heart as I...
你只是不如我那般了解国王的心
He had me whipped at the cart's arse
他把我绑在马车后面
from Fleet Bridge to Westminster!
从舰队河桥一直鞭打到威斯敏斯特
Would you see the stripes?!
你想看看那些鞭痕吗
John.
约翰
Let me take to him some words of conciliation...
让我传一些调解性的话给他
Apologise?
道歉吗?
John.
约翰
I?
我?
Her heart means well.
她是好心的
Madam, I thank you,
夫人 谢谢你了
but I would rather have another 500 lashes
不过我宁愿再受500鞭刑
ere I would kneel for forgiveness.
也不愿跪地求饶
The King must listen to the voice of reason in his Parliament
国王必须要听从议会的理智的意见
and dismiss his fat-witted advisors!
撤除他那些愚蠢的宠臣
We shall not live like slaves!
我们不能像奴隶般活着
Nor shall we loll in our beds
我们不能躺在床上
while he bring in an Irish Army or a Scotch Army to kill us!
等他派一些爱尔兰或苏格兰军队来杀死我们
I... I know nothing of an Irish Army.
我... 我对爱尔兰军队的事一无所知
Madam.
夫人
My friend loves his crown of thorns,
我的朋友讲话喜欢带刺
but God is at work in his honest heart.
但他的内心是善良的
If I may not know your name, know mine.
如果我无幸得知你的芳名 请记住我的
I am Thomas Rainsborough.
我叫托马斯·雷恩巴勒
The means to talk a King off his throne.
用言辞将国王推下宝座的人
King off his throne?
将国王推下宝座?
Sirrah, I will not stay and quarrel with you
小伙子 我不跟你争
for I see your life is a quarrel with itself.
你跟你自己就有得争了
When the world has turned, may you find your true nature.
当变天的时刻到来 愿你能找到你的真正归属
How will the world be turned, sir?
天怎么会变呢 先生?
When the first is last and the last is first.
当众生颠倒 伦常相悖
And where shall I be on that day?
那天我该去哪里呢?
You will be where you choose to be.
你会在你自己选择的地方
Farewell, gentle Lady.
再会 尊贵的女士
Who was the other, who had no words but "John"?
只说了句"约翰"的那人是谁?
A godly man, and a good man for a committee, I am told.
一个虔诚之人 我听说是个好议员
Sent from Cambridge to sit in the Commons.
剑桥派来的 位居下议院
Now that at last the King permits us to sit,
现在至少殿下允许我们在此有一席之位
let my first words in this new House be on injustice.
我在这新议院的第一句话要谈不公正
Hath not His Majesty sworn,
殿下难道不曾发誓
not to deny to any man either justice or right?
不剥夺任何人的公正或权利吗?
Then where is the justice for John Lilburne?
约翰·李尔本的公正何在?
That rots still in the Fleet
他不是至今还陷在舰队河监狱
by a sentence most illegal,
遭受的判决不仅非法
against the liberty of the subject,
违反国民应有的自由
bloody, wicked, barbarous and tyrannical?!
并且血腥 恶毒 野蛮而残暴?
Now we sit, we must listen to these voices
各位议员 我们必须倾听这些声音
or they will drown out our proceedings.
否则我们的进程将被其湮没
I, Oliver Cromwell,
我 奥利佛·克伦威尔
petition this House that by its own authority
请求下院行使自己的权利
it orders the immediate release of Honest John Lilburne!
立即释放正直的约翰·李尔本
You waste no words.
你话不多啊
What would you have me say?
你想要我说什么?
Did you think me...
你觉不觉得我...
"fat-witted"?
"头大无脑"?
Your journey was wasted.
你这一趟是在白费心机
You thought to bring a prize home for your husband, did you not?
您是想送份大礼给丈夫 不是吗?
He must not know.
一定不能让他知道
I will bring in your bags, my Lady.
我去拿您的行李 夫人
What thought you on Master Rainsborough?
你觉得雷恩巴勒大人如何?
If my Lady was a dinner,
如果夫人您是一盘美食
he would lick the plate clean.
他会把盘子舔得精光
No more?
没别的吗?
He sees into men's hearts.
他能看穿人心所想
"The world to turn."
"变天"
How may that be, think you?
你觉得会是怎么个变法?
He dreams.
他梦想着
On a world where no man needs a King to govern him.
人们不再受国王统治的世界
And perhaps, no woman her husband to govern her.
也许 女人们也不再受丈夫统治
Shall I bring in your bags, my Lady?
我可以去拿你的行李了吗 夫人?
Where got you those cuts?
你那些伤疤哪来的?
Fighting.
战斗
Where?
在哪?
Wherever there are wages.
无论哪里有佣金就行
Why are you here, Sexby?
你为什么在这里 塞斯比?
Why do you draw my water and carry logs to my fire?
为我挑水砍柴?
I am waiting, my Lady.
我在等待 夫人
For what?
等待什么?
For the killing to start.
等待杀戮开始
Killing?
杀戮?
One side will draw a sword.
总有一方会先刺出一剑
It is the world.
世事如此
Your horse waits on its straw.
您的马等着我去喂
And my Lord waits on you.
而阁下在等您
You are returned.
你回来了
How fares your friend?
你的朋友拜访的如何?
She is...
她...
She is much recovered, sir.
她好多了 先生
Cover yourself, sirrah.
把衣服穿好 小子
Harry.
哈里
My thoughts are with His Majesty.
我正想着殿下的事
A mob, urged on by traitors in the Parliament,
一伙暴民 受议会里的叛徒怂恿
has forced the release of Lilburne. This is anarchy.
胁迫释放了李尔本 这简直是无政府主义
Harry, do you not think that these grievances...?
哈里 你不觉得这些冤情...?
They have no grievances.
他们没有受冤
He is the King.
他是国王
They are his subjects.
他们是他的臣民
Of course, but might there not be...
当然 可难道没有...
It is not for you to think about.
这些不是你该操心的
We will go to London tomorrow.
我们明天就去伦敦
His Majesty has commanded the House to give up five old dogs
殿下命令议会除掉那五条老狗
that have bitten him these ten years.
这十多年他们一直撕咬着他
They still deny the King his right to rule.
他们无视殿下的统治权利
They're traitors, the House must surrender them.
他们是叛国者 议会必须将其铲除
And what if they refuse?
如果议会拒绝呢?
He will seize them.
他会逮捕他们
He will enter their Chamber?
他会亲自去议会?
It is his parliament.
那是他的议会
But to use force against...
可用武力对抗...
It is not for you to think about.
这些不是你该操心的
Harry.
哈里
Will you not come to me tonight?
今晚你不来我这吗?
Aye.
好的
If you will be silent.
如果你不这么多话
Why do men mock me?
为什么人们嘲笑我?
Who mocks you, Harry?
谁嘲笑你 哈里?
Even on my wedding day, I was mocked.
即便我婚礼那天 我还被人嘲笑
"A pleasure for all men."
"取悦所有的男人"
What?
什么?
Are you a whore, madam?
你是妓女吗 夫人?
I'm what you see, Harry. I'm what you know me to be.
我是你眼中所见 心中所念 哈里
Aye...
是啊...
by day.
在白天
But by night, what are you?
可到了夜晚 你又是谁?
When the Devil came to you...
当恶魔降临于你...
That you did tell me as a boy.
小时候你告诉过我的
Sir?
先生?
Aye, Satan, with his tongue unfurled.
没错 撒旦 吐出长长的舌头
I was a girl, I...
我只是个小女孩 我...
Did he enter you?
你被他附体了吗?
What?!
什么?!
Then wherefrom these noises at night?
那些夜晚的噪音发自何处?
Harry, why do we fight?
哈里 我们为什么争吵?
Are we not Harry and Angelica,
我们不再是哈里和安吉丽卡
best of friends?
最好的朋友了吗?
Boy, again.
又拿我当小男孩
Do you smell it?
你闻到了吗?
It's on the wind.
风中传来的气息
The House refuses.
议会拒绝了
I will be master of my enemies.
我会征服我的敌人
Follow me!
跟我来
Do not draw your sword...
不要轻易亮剑...
unless you be certain of the day.
除非你相信时机成熟
The King comes with armed men.
国王带兵前来
Gentlemen, a barge awaits you at the Watergate.
先生们 水闸处有船在等你们
Let them go, quickly.
让他们走 快点
If the King takes them, he is strong.
如果国王捉住他们 他就会得势
If he fails to take them, he is weak.
如果失败了 国王便会被削弱
Do not attack your enemy's house...
不要袭击你敌人的老巢...
..if he be gone from it.
...如果他已从那里跑掉
I had not thought he would do this, Thomas.
我没想到他会这么做 托马斯
Mr Speaker, I must for a time make bold with your chair.
议长大人 我必须占用你的椅子一会儿
Five of your members are charged with treason.
你这里有五个人被指控叛国罪
You will point them out to me.
你要把他们给我指出来
Sire, it is not my part to see
陛下 我无权发现
or speak anything but as this House desires me.
也无权指出什么 除非议会要求
Hear, hear!
好啊 好啊
No matter.
没关系
My eyes are as good as another's.
我的双眼和别人一样犀利
I can see all my birds have... flown.
我能看见我所有的鸟...飞到哪儿去了
Know the hour.
算准时机
And the minute.
每分
And the second.
每秒
It's lost.
失陷了
Harry, what is lost?
哈里 什么失陷了?
London is lost.
伦敦失陷了
(SHE SPEAKS IN FRENCH)
(法语)
We leave London as soon as it is dark.
天一黑我们就离开伦敦
The apprentice bands are sacking houses.
一帮学徒工们正四处洗劫
The militia is out and armed.
民兵在外面与我们兵戎相对
They come here to defend their Parliament.
他们来此倒戈议会
Majesty.
殿下
My dear, sweet girl, you must not trouble yourself.
我心爱的小姑娘 你一定别给自己找麻烦
Sire, there are matters Your Majesty may not fully understand.
殿下 您的麻烦也许只是个误会
Angelica.
安吉丽卡
Concerning the Parliament men.
关于议员们
I think they need not be your enemies, Your Majesty.
我想他们没必要与您为敌 陛下
There has been a mistake.
这里面有误会
A mistake?
误会?
I am...mistook?
我...误解了?
A thousand apologies, Your Majesty. Her mind is wild, still.
万分抱歉 殿下 她脑子糊涂了
Leave us.
退下
(SHE SPEAKS IN FRENCH)
(法语)
Wa...wa...wa...
开...开...开...
War.
开战
Edge Hill  Kineton 1642
金内顿村厄齐丘 1642年
The day depends on us!
这一天取决于我们
And we charge!
大家冲啊
Where's your honour, Sexby?
你效忠哪方 塞斯比?
Where are your men?
你的人呢?
Half way to Kineton, seeking you, sir.
在去金内顿的路上四下找您了吧 先生
Follow me.
跟我来
You lost your men, you seek them out.
你丢了自己的人 自己去把他们找回来
You're under my command, Sexby.
你要听命与我 塞斯比
I don't take orders from boys.
我不会听一个小男孩的命令
How came you by that?
你怎么得到的那个?
Give it to me.
把它给我
Take it from me.
自己来拿啊
I can have you shot for this.
我可以为此毙了你
Then why should I fight for you or your king?
那我何必还为你和你的国王卖命?
Come and fight me on the battlefield.
来战场跟我决斗吧
Hold fast, John!
撑住 约翰
Hold fast!
撑住
Welcome to paradise, sir!
欢迎来到天堂 先生
For liberty and justice!
为自由和公正
I see your world is turning!Sir
我看见你已经变天了 先生
Sexby!
塞斯比
Traitor!
叛国者
He's here, Thomas.
他在这 托马斯
The night has frozen his wounds.
寒夜冻住了他的伤口
Yet he breathes.
可他还有呼吸
Grab his legs...
抓住他的腿...
Both armies gave thanks to the same god
双方为同一场战争的胜利
for the same victory.
感谢同一个上帝
And in truth, the fight at Kineton settled nothing at all.
而事实上 金内顿的战斗什么都没解决
It was only the beginning.
一切只是刚刚开始
As the seasons turned,
随着四季流转
ever more blood was spilled in all corners of the land.
更多鲜血洒向大地每个角落
Croyland Abbey,The Fens Christmas Day 1643
费恩地 克罗兰修道院 1643年圣诞
You thought right, Thomas.
被你算准了 托马斯
They look not for this, not come by floodwater.
他们没想到这个 没想到随洪水而来
Nor on this day, Oliver.
也没想到在这一天 奥利佛
Make ready the guns, Edward.
准备好火炮 爱德华
Thomas. Must there truly be no warning?
托马斯 真的不用警告吗?
None.
不用
We are too few to storm them.
打猛攻我们人太少
Women and children...
妇女和孩子...
Aye. They must feel terror in their hearts.
是的 他们一定从心底感到恐惧
Fire the first gun.
放第一炮
Fire the first gun and reload.
放第一炮 重新装药
Fire the second.
放第二炮
Fire the second gun and reload.
放第二炮 重新装药
We are ready, sir.
准备好了 先生
Hold.
等等
Thomas, surely they see how few we are.
托马斯 他们肯定看见我们有多少人了
All that matter's is this man's spirit.
关键只在这个人的精神
If I break it, your men need not draw their swords.
如果我能打垮它 你的人无需拔剑出鞘
Is this how men fight, sir?
真正的男人就是这样战斗的吗 先生?
Hear this. God sent these floods to trap you.
听听 上帝遣来洪水将你们陷入困境
Now he sends you Rainsborough and Cromwell,
现在又派来雷恩巴勒和克伦威尔
like Joshua and Gideon,
就像约书亚和基甸
to drown you in fire and blood.
用血与火湮灭你们 (旧约 士师记)
You cannot withstand us. We have 20 cannon.
你们抵挡不了我们 我们有二十门加农炮
Our duty is clear, sirs.
我们的职责很明确 先生们
You will command the surrender now.
你马上下令投降
If you do, you may retreat,
服从我们
bag and baggage when the waters go.
你们可以随潮水撤离 全身而退
Sirs...
诸位...
Else your walls will suffer more ordnance.
否则只会遭受更多炮火
My engineers will dig beneath you
我的工兵会掘下地道
and we will blow you all to atoms.
把你们炸为齑粉
Your men will receive no quarter.
你的人不要心存侥幸
Those that breathe will go to the Indies as slaves.
若有生还者 将发配印度为奴
Decide now.
决定吧
Your time is borrowed, sir.
你的时间已经透支了 先生
Will you grant us what remains of this blessed day to pray together
这圣日余下的时间能留给我们祈祷吗
Colonel Rainsborough?
雷恩巴勒上校?
No, sir.
不 先生
You blaspheme by giving the Son of God a birthday party.
为圣子操办生日本身就是渎神
This is a day like any other.
今日和平日一般无二
Angelica, the King asks me to tell you
安吉丽卡 国王让我转告你
he has recalled Harry from the West Country.
他已从西南部召回了哈里
Then I can go to Fanshawe again?
那我可以回范肖了?
No, no, child. You are to wait till Harry sends for you.
不行 孩子 你得等哈里派人来接你
Bring him in.
让他进来
Away!
退下
Stand.
平身
Well, speak.
说话呀
Sire, on Christmas Day just gone,
陛下 昨日圣诞节
the Abbey at Croyland was taken.
克罗兰修道院陷落了
Taken?
陷落?
How, taken?
怎么个陷落法?
Surrendered, sire.
投降了 陛下
To Colonels Cromwell and Rainsborough.
投降克伦威尔和雷恩巴勒上校
Sire, we could not have resisted them.
陛下 我们无力抵御他们
Surrendered?
投降?
Without...a fight?
没有...反抗吗?
Well...
好吧
You, sir, will never command men hereafter.
你 先生 不会再领兵作战了
It seems now my enemies need only look upon my power
似乎如今敌人只须一瞥
and it takes to its heels.
我的军队便俯首称臣
I must tell you all,
我告诉你们大家
while they have more stomach than we have for the fight,
如果他们比我们斗志更强
none of us will see London ever again.
我们谁也别想再看到伦敦了
Save yourself, madam!
自卫吧 夫人
What's going on?         Go, go!
怎么回事?      走 快走
Find them.
追捕他们
You'll watch them hang.
你要亲眼看他们上绞架
Slowly.
慢慢死去
You were not...
你没被...
..touched?
染指吧?
I was never more glad to see you.
我从没有这么高兴见到你
My letter was clear. You were to wait to be brought out.
我的信很明确 你要等人去接
I thought I was...
我以为我...
You thought?
你以为?
You thought to pay no heed to my wishes.
你以为我的意愿一钱不值
Men are dead because you thought.
你一念断送了几条人命
I was wrong.
我错了
It was done because...
这只是因为...
I missed my friend Harry.
我想念我的朋友哈里
Did he not miss me?
他不想念我吗?
You reach for your boy.
你想找你的男孩
You will not find him again.
你再也找不到他了
I am Colonel Harry Fanshawe.
我是哈里·范肖上校
I am yours to command, Colonel.
我由您发落 上校
Amen.
阿门
Let down your hair.
披下头发
Show yourself to me.
把你自己展示出来
Oh, my husband...
哦 我的夫君
My true, brave husband.
我忠诚 勇敢的夫君
You are my master.
你是我的主人
I am yours.
我是你的
My true...
我忠诚...
Madam!
夫人
These are the words of the whores in my soldiers' camps!
这种话是我士兵帐中的娼妓们说的
Then, Harry...
那么 哈里
..I commend to you to your soldiers...
我将你交托给你的士兵
..and your soldiers to their whores.
将你的士兵交托给他们的娼妓
Where you may command, I will ever be your dutiful wife.
你能下令之处 我会永远做你忠实的妻子
Where you may not, I can be nothing but what I am.
你不能下令之处 我只能做我自己
Parliamentary Camp Newbury October 1644
纽布利议会军营地 1644年十月
Horses for the Earl of Manchester.
曼彻斯特伯爵的马
Does the Commander-in-Chief know our plans, General?
总司令知道计划了吗 将军?
The King marches on us, my lord.
王党正向我们开来 大人
I have a plan to assault his guns at first peep,
我计划拿下他们的火炮
from behind his own lines.
从背后包抄
We shall devise some signal for your lordship
得商定些信号
when it is time to take to the field.
让爵爷您知道何时进攻
I will not need your signal, Colonel Rainsborough,
我不需要你的信号 雷恩巴勒上校
and I did not loll asleep, General,
你先前简报的时候 将军
when you spoke your plans earlier.
我也没打瞌睡
I believe the King will not press the fight.
我相信保王党不会缠斗不休
Let the winter come on. Let time heal our wounds.
等冬天到来吧 时间会消弭我们的创伤
For myself, I'd march to Oxford and pull him from his lair.
我本人倒宁愿冲到牛津 把他从老巢里揪出来
Would not you, General?
你不想吗 将军?
Gentlemen, we must consider what we do.
先生们 我们得三思而后行
If we fight the King a hundred times and we beat him 99 times
我们一百次中99次战胜国王
he will be King still.
他还是国王
But if he beat us but once, we shall be hanged.
可他只要战胜我们一次 我们就会身首异处
We shall lose our estates.
家破人亡
Sir, I have none to lose.
先生 我没有家产可破
My lord, if this be so,
阁下 若是如此
then why did we take up arms at first?
当初我们何必开战?
Then let us make peace, on any terms, be it never so base.
干脆讲和吧 再低贱的条件都无所谓
Are your men in readiness, then?
你的人准备就绪了吗?
Armed without and within, my lord.
从身到心斗志昂扬 阁下
I'm told...
我听说
that none of your officers are men of estate,
你的军官无一人有产业
but such as are common men.
全是平头百姓
Yet godly and precious, sir.
这话不假 先生
They are in this quarrel for their conscience' sake,
他们是为良心而战
not for pay.
不是为报酬
I pray you look them over.
请您检阅他们
The day draws on.
天色晚了
I pray you.
我请求您
For most surely it would raise their spirits even higher
因为最激发士气的莫过于
to look upon the face of their Commander-in-Chief.
他们总司令的面孔
For what is our purpose in this fight,
此战唯一目的
but to rid England of the thieving abuses of privilege
难道不是消灭窃国的特权阶级
and to take back our common inheritance?
夺回我们共有的遗产?
A rich man is but a man who is a burden on to other men.
阔人只是其他人肩上的负担
Even an earl is but a man.
伯爵也不过凡夫俗子
Who is this?
这是谁?
Major Lilburne,
李尔本中校
that did fight most desperately at Kineton
在金内顿和近来的马斯顿大捷中
and in our late victory at Marston field.
奋勇作战的一位
Lilburne - the man who would have us all level.
李尔本 人人平等的鼓吹家
Will he not bow?
他不肯鞠躬吗?
John...will you not bow to his lordship?
约翰 你不朝爵爷鞠一躬吗?
Bow, sir, and all will be well.
鞠躬 先生 我们就相安无事
All will not be well in this land
不可能相安无事
until the Earl of Manchester is but plain Mr Montague.
除非曼彻斯特伯爵变成凡人蒙塔古先生
You will hang, sir!
准备上绞架吧 先生
He will not hang. I will be hanged first.
他不会上绞架 除非先绞死我 先生
Edward!         My lord.
爱德华      阁下
Perhaps the earl did not see
也许伯爵没看见
how bravely this man fought at Marston.
他在马斯顿一役中如何英勇
For it was somewhat dark
因为他上战场前
before he entered the field of battle himself.
天早就黑了
You, sir, are another Leveller!
你 先生 你也是平等派
And I will have no Levellers in my command!
我麾下绝不要平等派
Bow, or I'll hang you myself.
鞠躬 不然我亲手绞死你
Edward, you were too hot.
爱德华 你太过火了
But I'll speak to the earl and he will relent.
不过我会找伯爵说说 他会开恩的
Do not spend your breath.
别费唾沫了
I will fight for this parliament no more.
我不给这个议会卖命了
Where is liberty
这算哪门子自由
when Freeborn John must bow to a hog in armour?
自由人约翰得给那个蠢猪鞠躬?
Fare you well.
后会有期
He spoke the truth.
他说得对
There are too many like Mr Montague that
有太多蒙塔古先生这种人
have too much to lose by our victory.
对我们的胜利太多顾虑
Goodnight.
晚安
You were right, Thomas.
你说得对 托马斯
Soon we must move towards Oxford and the King's lair.
我们就快开往牛津 打进国王老巢了
And in our way, there are some great houses
途中有些显赫的家族
that we must secure.
我们必须拿下
Nay, that you must secure.
不 是你必须拿下
Colonel Fanshawe. I am Colonel Thomas Rainsborough.
范肖上校 我是托马斯雷恩巴勒上校
I know you who you are.
我认得你是谁
I will accept no bargain nor hear no threats from you.
别想跟我交易 也别想威胁我
Do your worst.
尽管放马过来
My lady and her women will leave within the hour.
我夫人和女眷们一小时内离开
So be it.
那就这样吧
My wife.
我妻子
I will write you a pass to Oxford, my lady.
我给你开张去牛津的通行证 夫人
We are busy in the county.
我们这里很忙
I will need no pass, sir.
我不需要通行证 先生
This is the house that I was born in.
我生于此 长于此
If you wish to take it from us,
你想夺走它
you will wade through blood to do it.
就准备血战到底吧
This is not Croyland Abbey.
这里不是克罗兰修道院
Is this not so, my lord?
不是吗 阁下?
The ladies will be ready within the hour.
女士们会一小时内开拔
Husband?
夫君?
Madam.
夫人
Hear your husband, for I mean to do my duty here.
夫人 服从你的夫君 我会履行我的职责
And I mine...sir.
我也会...先生
You will leave, madam!
你必须走 夫人
I will not, sir.
我不走 先生
Angelica, you are the dearest creature in the world to me...
安吉丽卡 你是这世上我最珍重的人
Then let me stand beside you.
那让我和你一道吧
Rainsborough has never failed in a siege.
雷恩巴勒攻城从不失败
He will destroy the house and all in it.
他会摧毁这所房子和里面的一切
Then where else should I be?
那我还能在哪呢?
I will stay at all costs.
我会不惜一切代价留下
And die by your side.
与你同生共死
Then all is lost.
那么一切都完了
Utterly lost.
全完了
Your Majesty...
陛下...
Be silent.
住嘴
You should have obeyed your husband.
你应该服从你的夫君
And you, sir...
而你 先生
..you should have subdued your wife.
你应该驾驭你的妻子
Stay in Oxford if you will, madam,
想留在牛津就留下吧 夫人
but expect nothing from the Queen's household evermore.
但别再指望皇后的眷顾了
I will accept any commission from Your Majesty,
我愿接受陛下委任的任何职位
however base or of low rank...
无论如何卑微 或低贱...
No, sir.
不 先生
You will prepare yourself... to meet God.
你准备好...见上帝吧
Your Majesty...?
陛下?
He forgiveth and absolveth them that truly repent,
诚心悔悟的人必得他赦免
so that at the last, we may come to his eternal joy...
为使我们最终永享平安喜乐
..through Jesus Christ Our Lord.
为耶稣基督我们的主
Amen.
阿门
You must say "amen".
你得说"阿门"
Surely the King does this only to fright me?
国王当然只是吓唬我吧?
Halt!
立定
Stand left!
向左转
Where is my wife?
我妻子在哪?
Harry!
哈里
Be brief, madam.
简短些 夫人
Farewell, sweet friend.
永别了 亲爱的朋友
I have done this, Harry.
这是我的错 哈里
I have done this!
是我的错
Remember me.
记住我
Remember your boy...
记住你的男孩
who loved his sweet playfellow more than life.
他爱他亲爱的玩伴更甚于生命
Pray to God for me, Angelica.
为我祈祷上帝 安吉丽卡
Please God...
求你 上帝
Take aim...
瞄准
Please, God, if you hear me, I beg you...
求你 上帝 如果你能听见 我乞求你...
Fire!
开火